<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<ri:Resource
	xsi:type="vstd:Standard"
	created="2016-07-09T08:00:00Z"
	updated="2023-05-23T14:03:00"
	status="active"
	xmlns:vr="http://www.ivoa.net/xml/VOResource/v1.0"
	xmlns:vstd="http://www.ivoa.net/xml/StandardsRegExt/v1.0"
	xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
	xmlns:ri="http://www.ivoa.net/xml/RegistryInterface/v1.0"
	xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.ivoa.net/xml/VOResource/v1.0 http://www.ivoa.net/xml/VOResource/v1.0
						http://www.ivoa.net/xml/StandardsRegExt/v1.0 http://www.ivoa.net/xml/StandardsRegExt/v1.0
						http://www.ivoa.net/xml/RegistryInterface/v1.0 http://www.ivoa.net/xml/RegistryInterface/v1.0">

	<title>Observation Data Model Core Components and its Implementation in the Table Access
		Protocol</title>
	<identifier>ivo://ivoa.net/std/obscore</identifier>
	<curation>
		<publisher>IVOA</publisher>

		<creator>
			<name>Louys, M.</name>
		</creator>
		<creator>
			<name>Tody, D.</name>
		</creator>
		<creator>
			<name>Dowler, P.</name>
		</creator>
		<creator>
			<name>Durand, D.</name>
		</creator>
		<creator>
			<name>Michel, L.</name>
		</creator>
		<creator>
			<name>Bonnarel, F.</name>
		</creator>
		<creator>
			<name>Micol, A.</name>
		</creator>

		<!-- this should be the date of the last recommendation -->
		<date role="update">2017-05-09</date>
		<version>1.1</version> <!-- the document version -->
		<contact>
			<name>IVOA Data Model Working Group</name>
			<email>dm@ivoa.net</email>
		</contact>
	</curation>
	<content>
		<subject>Virtual observatory</subject>
		<subject>Metadata modeling</subject>
		<!-- you can give further keywords, one per subject element;
    use the IVOA thesaurus if possible:
    http://www.ivoa.net/rdf/Vocabularies/vocabularies-20091007/IVOAT/IVOAT.html
    -->

		<description>
			This document defines the core components of the Observation data model
			that are necessary to perform data discovery when querying data centers
			for astronomical observations of interest. It exposes use-cases to be carried out,
			explains the model and provides guidelines for its implementation as a data access
			service based on the Table Access Protocol (TAP).
			It aims at providing a simple model easy to understand and to implement by data
			providers that wish to publish their data into the Virtual Observatory. This
			interface integrates data modeling and data access aspects in a single service and
			is named ObsTAP. It will be referenced as such in the IVOA registries.
			In this document, the Observation Data Model Core Components (ObsCoreDM) defines
			the core components of queryable metadata required for global discovery of
			observational data. It is meant to allow a single query to be posed to TAP
			services at multiple sites to perform global data discovery without having to
			understand the details of the services present at each site. It defines a minimal
			set of basic metadata and thus allows for a reasonable cost of implementation by
			data providers. As with most of the VO Data Models, ObsCoreDM makes use of STC,
			Utypes, Units and UCDs. The ObsCoreDM can be serialized as a VOTable. ObsCoreDM
			can make reference to more complete data models such as Characterisation DM,
			Spectrum DM or Simple Spectral Line Data Model (SSLDM). ObsCore shares a large set
			of common concepts with DataSet Metadata Data Model (Cresitello-Dittmar et al. 2016)
			which binds together most of the data model concepts from the above models in a
			comprehensive and more general frame work. This current specification on the
			contrary provides guidelines for implementing these concepts using the TAP protocol
			and answering ADQL queries. It is dedicated to global discovery.
		</description>
		<referenceURL>http://ivoa.net/documents/ObsCore/</referenceURL>
		<type>Other</type>
		<contentLevel>Research</contentLevel>
	</content>

	<endorsedVersion status="rec">1.1</endorsedVersion>

	<key>
		<name>core-1.1</name>
		<description>The TAP/ADQL table schema for ObsCore version 1.1 .
			Examples for TAPv1.0
		</description>
	</key>

</ri:Resource>